Guide to the Miscellaneous Personal Papers Collection
Yale University Divinity School Library
Miscellaneous Personal Papers Collection
1692-2013
RG 30
Yale University Divinity School Library
128
308+ boxes
The Miscellaneous Personal Papers record group is an open collection consisting of the correspondence, diaries, writings and/or other papers and memorabilia of various individuals. This collection contains papers of individuals who were Yale faculty members, alumni/ae, clergy, ecumenical workers, or missionaries in areas other than China.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired from various sources.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers
Biographical / Historical
See the alphabetical listing for biographical information about the individuals included in this record group.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains correspondence, diaries, writings and/or other papers and memorabilia of various individuals, including former Yale faculty members, clergymen and missionaries to areas other than China. The papers of these men and women have been placed in the Miscellaneous Personal Papers record group because the quantity or substance of the material did not warrant a separate record group.
Arrangement
I. Individuals A-L
II. Individuals M-Y
Congregational churches -- United States; Missions -- India; Diaries; Clergy; Educators; Missionaries; Archer, John Clark, 1881-1957; Backus, Simon; Bacon, Benjamin Wisner, 1860-1932; Beebe, David Lewis, 1763-1803; Beebe, James, 1717 or 1718-1785; Bellamy, Joseph, 1719-1790; Bergmann, W. (Wilhelm), 1899-1987; Borden, William, 1887-1913; Brainerd, David, 1718-1747; Carson, Arthur L. (Arthur Leroy), 1895-; Chamberlain, Jacob, 1835-1908; Chambers, William Nesbitt, 1853-1934; Cleary, Edward L.; Cooley, Frank L. (Frank Leonard), 1920-; Corey, Clara Watts Long, 1868-; Ferris, Theodore Parker, 1908-1972; Fisher, George Park, 1827-1909; Goodwin, Francis; Hartshorne, Hugh, 1885-1967; Kidder, Daniel P. (Daniel Parish), 1815-1891; Large, Dwight S.; Little, Charles, 1818-1892; Maurer, Oscar E. (Oscar Edward), 1878-; McQuary, Rodney L., 1888-1977; Miller, Jonathan, 1761-1831; Morris, Thomas, 1792-; Rice, Edwin Botts; Schubert, Paul, 1900-; Torrey, Charles Cutler, 1863-1956; Warnshuis, A. L. (Abbe Livingston), 1877-1958; Williams, J. (John), 1817-1899; Williams, William Frederic, 1818-1871; Wishard, Luther D. (Luther Deloraine), 1854-1925; Episcopal Church; Yale University. Divinity School
- Individuals A-L, Series I
  - Agapides, John
    Biographical / Historical
    Agapides was a Greek lawyer.
    - Notebook containing handwritten translation of "Greek Evangelical Communities of Pontus" by John Agapides, Lawyer: Printing House of Nico S. Zlatanos, Thessaloniki. Translated by Charles T. Riggs, 1948 (Box 449, Folder 4)
  - Alderson, Cecil William
    Alderson (1900-1968) was Anglican Bishop of Damaraland, Bloemfontein, and Mashonaland in southern Africa from 1949 to 1968.
    - Album of photographs taken while Alderson was Bishop of Mashonaland (1957-1968) and of his funeral service (Box 455, Folder 3)
    - Loose photographs: Portraits of Bishop Alderson, ca, 1920s-1960s (Box 455, Folder 4)
    - Loose photographs: Documention of his work as Bishop, ca. 1950s-1960s (Box 455, Folder 5-6)
    - Memorabilia, biographical information, 1942, 1957, no date (Box 455, Folder 7)
  - Allison, Walter and Grace
    Walter Leslie Allison and Grace Fleck Allison served in North India from 1920 to 1954 as educational and evangelical missionaries under the Board of Foreign Missions of the Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A. After WLA died in 1944, GFA taught at Woodstock School and the Prentiss Girls' School in Etah.
    - Diary: entitled "Daily Doings of Allisons 1920-1923 Vol I" - handwritten entries in bound ledger book provide detailed information regarding activities (Box 384, Folder 1)
    - Diary: "1924-1941 Vol. II": handwritten entries in bound notebook. (Box 384, Folder 2)
    - Circular letters and reports, primarily written by Grace Allison, from Etawah, Gwalior, Landour, Mainpuri, incl. re. educational and evangelical work, Sunday School work, social events, Woodstock School for missionary children, distribution of tracts and Gospel portions; biographical sketches of GFA, 1923-1954 (Box 384, Folder 3-6)
  - Alter, Martha Payne
    Martha Payne Alter (1890-1951) was a missionary to India from 1916 to 1951, serving under the United Presbyterian Church of North America. She was the mother of James Payne Alter, whose papers are held in YDSL Record Group No. 84. This collection contains the originals of letters that were published in Letters from India to America 1916-1951 by Martha Payne Alter, edited by Ellen and Bob Alter. An index to the letters is contained in the first folder.
    - Index to letters; Letters written en route to India; from Sialkot, Landour, Simla Trek, Jhelum, 1916 Oct-1917 Dec (Box 379, Folder 1-4)
    - From Jhelum and Mussoorie, 1918 Jan-1919 May (Box 379, Folder 5-7)
    - From Kashmir, Murree, Sialkot, Jhelum, camp, Chakwal, 1919 May-1920 Dec (Box 379, Folder 8-12)
    - From camp, Landour, Sialkot, 1921 (Box 379, Folder 13-14)
    - From Jhelum, furlough in U.S.A., 1922-1925 Nov (Box 379, Folder 15-17)
    - Incl. from Abbotabad, Landour, 1925 Nov-1932 (Box 380, Folder 1-10)
    - En route to Taxila, from Landour, en route to U.S.A., en route to India, 1933, 1935 (Box 381, Folder 1-2)
    - From Sialkot, Jhelum, Rawalpindi, Landour, Kashmir, and en route to U.S.A., 1935 Oct-1938 Dec (Box 381, Folder 3-9)
    - En route to India, from Woodstock School, 1939 Nov-1943 Dec (Box 381, Folder 10-14)
    - En route to U.S.A., enroute to India, 1944-1946 (Box 381, Folder 15-16)
    - From Rawalpindi, Landour, 1947-1950 (Box 381, Folder 17-20)
    - En route to U.S.A., from Berkeley, 1951 (Box 381, Folder 21-22)
  - Archer, John Clark
    Archer was born in 1881. Education: 1905 - B.A., Hiram College;1914 - B.D. and M.A., Yale; 1922 - Ph.D., Yale; Employment: 1915-1916 - Lecturer on Missions, Yale; 1916-1924 - Assistant Professor, Yale;1924-1927 - Associate Professor, Yale; 1927-1932 - Professor of Missions and Comparative Religion; 1932-1950 - Hoober Professor of Comparative Religion; 1950 - Professor Emeritus; 1932-1935 - Curator of Collection on Comparative Religion; He died 1957 Jul 7.
    - Correspondence: (1920, 1930-1968, n.d.), arranged chronologically. Early correspondence with Luther Weigle and Andrew Keogh relates to courses offered by Archer and the Day Missions Library. Includes a few letters to Archer's wife after his death. Letters deal with Archer's writings and the 25th reunion of his Divinity School class of 1914, as well as the ambassadorship of Chester Bowles in India: correspondence with Jawaharlal Nehru and Indian diplomats. (5 folders) (Box 87)
    - Writings: Articles and Papers (1922-1954), arranged alphabetically by title (There is also a bound volume of articles by Archer in the library's restricted circulation collection) (Box 87)
    - Writings: Book Reviews (1938-1946). List of additional reviews included (1 folder) (Box 87)
    - Notes (n.d.) (1 folder) (Box 87)
    - Bibliographies; 2 parish programs of missionary education (1920, 1922) (1 folder) (Box 87)
    - Printed Material: Primarily newspaper clippings (1945-1960) (2 folders) (Box 87)
    - Memorabilia: Indian flags and hat (Box 87)
    - Biographical documentation: Memorial service for JCA, 1958 (1 folder) (Box 87)
    - Photographs and postcards: Mostly of Asia, unidentified (1 folder) (Box 87)
  - Arthur, James Hope and Clara Stevens
    James Hope Arthur was an American Baptist missionary in Japan 1873 to 1877. See biographical information in first folder.
    - Genealogical materials related to familie of Clara Stevens Arthur and James Hope Arthur, birth certificates, burial plot certificates, 1844-1924, no date (Box 452, Folder 12-14)
    - Correspondence of Clara, James Sr., and son James, Jr., aunt Jenny, and others, 1872-1924 (Box 452, Folder 15-17)
    - Diary of James Hope Arthur written in Japan and California, Children's story, 1877 (Box 452, Folder 18)
  - Austin, Ralph V.
    Austin (1895-1962) graduated from Yale Divinity School in 1924 after serving in the U.S. Army during WWI and attending Butler College. He served primarily Congregational churches in Connecticut, Indiana, and Wisconsin. This collection documents his ministry and involvement in social issues such as desegregation and migrant workers.
    - Letters written to family members while in military service during World War I., 1917-1918 (Box 40, Folder 1-3)
      Austin joined the U.S. Army in July 1917 and sailed for France in December with the Second Division, serving in field hospitals in France, in Germany as part of the occupying forces, and in the United Kingdom. He was discharged in 1919.
      Scope and Contents
      Folder 1 contains notes that are selected excerpts from WWI letters and diary.
    - Diary / journal entries describing experiences in military training in U.S. and service in France and Germany; copy of Honorable Discharge from the U.S. Army, 1919 October 13, 1917-1919 (Box 40, Folder 4-6)
    - Documentation of four months study in London under auspices of American Army Educational Commission, 1919 March - August (Box 40, Folder 7)
    - Postcards and photographs, pamphlet on The Second Division, collected poems from period of World War I service, 1917-1919 (Box 40, Folder 8)
    - Documentation primarily from period serving at Winchester Center, Connecticut and attending Yale Divinity School, 1920-1925 (Box 40, Folder 9-12)
      These folders include the contents of a file box that was divided alphabetically and contained letters and other documents. A few documents date from after Vernon moved back to Indiana from Connecticut.
    - Documentation from period serving at Indianapolis, IN, 1925-1926 (Box 41, Folder 1-3)
      These folders include the contents of a file box that was divided alphabetically and contained letters and other documents.
    - Documentation from period serving at Rhinelander, Wisconsin, 1938-1949 (Box 41, Folder 4)
      Includes letters to/from Austin's wife Helen Mayo Austin, whom he married in 1922.
    - Documentation from period serving at Hayward, Wisconsin and letters of Helen Austin following death of RVA in 1962, 1948-1967 (Box 41, Folder 5)
      Includes biographical statement prepared for church in Hayward
    - Notes and writings, 1941-1944, no date (Box 41, Folder 6)
    - Biographical documentation and memorabilia, 1946-1962, no date (Box 41, Folder 7)
      Includes 5-page family and personal history written by RVA, obituary and tributes
    - Photographs, 1948-1973, no date (Box 41, Folder 8)
  - Ayi, Francois
    Ayi is a member of the royal family of Togo and was crowned king in 1994, though some question the legitimacy of his position. In 1997 Ayi founded the Royal Green Cross, an international youth volunteer program.
    - Documentation regarding Ayi and the Royal Green Cross organization, 1992, 1998-2000 (Box 285, Folder 4)
    - Photographs (Box 285, Folder 5-6)
  - Backus, Charles
    1749 - Born in Franklin, CT; 1769 - Graduated from Yale College; 1773 - Began service as postor of Congregational Church in Somers, CT; 1803 - Died
    - One manuscript sermon "Preached before the Reverend Clergy of the State of Connecticut, in the College Chapel in New Haven on the morning after the Commencement Sept. 11th, 1788" (Box 216)
  - Backus, Simon (1701-1745)
    1701 - Born in Norwich, CT, son of Joseph and Elizabeth (Huntington) Backus; 1724 - Graduated from Yale College; 1727 - Ordained, served Newington parish in Wethersfield, CT; 1729 - Married to Eunice Edwards, sister of Jonathan Edwards; 1737/38 - Son Simon born; 1745 - Sent by colony authorities to Louisburg, Cape Breton as chaplain to the 350 Connecticut troops stationed there to prevent a recapture of the post by the French. Was taken ill and died there.
    - 22 manuscript sermons delivered by Backus in various Connecticut churches. Organized chronologically by earliest date noted on the sermon, 1724-1739 (3 folders) (Box 216)
    - Account record (1735-1736); goods and services received, with prices marked. (1 folder) (Box 216)
    - Letter written in by grandson, which includes biographical information regarding Simon Backus and his son Simon (Box 216)
  - Backus, Simon (1737/38-1823)
    1737/38 - Born in Newington parish, Wethersfield, CT, son of Simon and Eunice (Edwards) Backus; 1759 - Graduated from Yale College; 1762 - Ordained as first pastor of a Congregational church just gathered in the southern part of Hadley, MA, now Granby, CT.; 1784 - Moved to Hanover, NH, and filled vacant pulpits in that vicinity; 1790 - Returned to CT, installed at Congregational Church in North Bristol, now North Madison; 1801 - Dismissed from his post after becoming involved in serious difficulties with the people of his parish. Lived in area for another 15 years, becoming increasingly impoverish. Later lived with his son in Bridgeport.; 1823 - Died in Stratford, CT
    - 136 manuscript sermons organized chronologically by earliest date noted on the sermon (1760-1808) (Box 216–217)
    - 42 undated manuscript sermons (Box 217–218)
    - Sermon fragments (8 folders) (Box 218)
    - Miscellany including account records and notes (1772, n.d.) (1 folder) (Box 218)
    - Material received with the Backus papers: six items, including correspondence (1894-1895; 1905, n.d.) related to Julia H. Kinney (1 folder) (Box 218)
  - Bacon, Benjamin Wisner
    1860 - Born; 1881 - B.A., Yale; 1884 - B.D., Yale; 1892 - M.A., Yale; 1893 - D.D., Western Reserve University; 1895 - Litt.D., Syracuse University; 1896 - Instructor in New Testament Greek, Yale; 1897-1928 - Buckingham Professor of New Testament Criticism and Interpretation, Yale Divinity School; 1928-1932 - Professor Emeritus; 1929-1930 - Shaffer Lecturer, Yale; 1932 - Died
    - Editorial re. BWB written by Frank C. Porter for New Haven Journal Courier, 1932 (Box 101)
    - Address delivered by H. H. Tweedy at memorial service for Bacon in Battell Chapel, April 26, 1932 (Box 101)
    - Photograph, two clippings re. Bacon's retirement (Box 101)
    - Correspondence (1888-1929) (5 folders): arranged alphabetically by author; primarily letters from Bacon's colleagues in Europe, including such notables as Harnack, Moffat (Box 101)
    - Writings: Articles and addresses are arranged alphabetically by title. A list of writings is located in the "A" folder, as well as a bibliography of Bacon's works, 1903-1934 (Box 101–102)
    - Miscellaneous: includes notes written by Bacon, a review of one of his aricles, two postcard (Box 102)
    - Writings about Bacon: "B. W. Bacon on John and Mark", 32 p. paper prepared for SBL convention, Dallas, Nov. 1980, by D. Moody Smith, Duke University. (Box 102)
  - Baldwin, Henry
    Missionary in New York City.
    - Diary of a city missionary dating from 1864 to 1866. Describes Baldwin's visitations, recruiting of Sunday School members, and other daily events. Includes detailed description and quotations of conversations with people in his missionary area. Streets mentioned in the 14th ward where he served: Mulberry, Hester, Jersey, Grand, Centre, Mott, Crosby (Box 106)
  - Baldwin, Russell E.
    Baldwin, formerly known as Ulric Lanoue, was an American Baptist missionary in the Belgian Congo, primarily in Kimpese, from 1932 to 1942.
    - "No Regrets" Letters from Belgian Congo 1932-1942": typescript volume of transcribed letters written by Baldwin from the Belgian Congo, primarily to family in the U.S., describing his missionary activities, with 1982 letters describing a return trip to the Congo, 1932-1942, 1982 (Box 453, Folder 7)
  - Balcke, Antoine
    Balcke was a Belgian Catholic priest serving under the Scheut Mission in Belgian Congo. He was stationed at Kalua, Yambuku and Bumba during the 1930s-1940s.
    - Photographs: groups of Western clergy, African students and clergy, military groups, 1930s-1940s (Box 455, Folder 8)
    - Photographs: scenes of mission work, church in Bumba, scenes in Yambuku, 1930s-1940s (Box 455, Folder 9)
    - Memorabilia: ordination card, autographed bookplate, postcard, 1920, 1948, no date (Box 455, Folder 10)
  - Ballantine, Henry W.
    Ballantine was a missionary in India serving under the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions from 1852 to 1865.
    - Handwritten letter from Ballantine to his children, written from Bombay, describes work in a school for boys of low caste, 1864 (Box 456, Folder 4)
  - Ballard, Josiah
    1806 - Born in Peterborough, NH; 1826-1829 - Attended Academy at Monson, MA; 1833 - Graduated from Yale; 1834-1835 - Studied thoelogy with the Rev. D. Whiton of Antrim, NH. Married his daughter Elizabeth; 1835-1863 - Ordained as pastor and served churches at Chesterfield, NH, Plympton, Sudbury, Ipswich, and Carlisle, MA; 1863 - Died
    - Manuscript sermon, the last preached by Ballard (1863) (Box 97)
    - Memorial written about Ballard and his wife by their children in 1876. 14 pp. (Box 97)
  - Balliet, Thomas Minard
    1852 Mar 1 Born in Lehighton, PA; 1876 B.A., Franklin and Marshall College; 1877-1878 Attended Yale Divinity School; 1878-1879 Attended Reformed Church Theological Seminary; 1879 M.A., Franklin and Marshall; 1879-1904 Taught, was superintendent of school in various communities in PA, IL, MA; 1904-1919 Dean of School of Pedagogy, N.Y. University; 1942 Died.
    - One bound volume of holograph notes taken while a student at the Yale Divinity School (1877-1878) - lectures on the Epistle to the Galatians. (Box 291, Folder 2)
  - Banninga, John J.
    Banninga (1875-1963) graduated from Hope College in 1898 andWestern Theological Seminary in 1901. John and his wife, Sophia Maria "Mary" Damson left for India in 1901 and served there for forty-two years. In 1917, John became the principal of the Union Theological Seminary at Pasumalai in South India, a position he would hold for 25 years.
    - Newspaper clipping re. return of Banningas to Michigan ca. 1906; printed circular letters describing Banningas' work in Pasumalai, ca. 1906, 1911, 1940, 1941 (Box 423, Folder 3)
  - Barone, Alfred D.
    A native of Italy, Rev. Dr. Alfred D. Barone converted to Protestantism and established Protestant missions throughout Italy under the auspices of the Home Mission Society of London. He came to the U.S. in 1899 and preached in CT and MA. In 1910 he established his own missionary and educational work under the name of the Alpha and Omega Assembly, based in New Haven, CT and Brooklyn NY.
    - Handwritten ms. by ADB, "The Requisites necessary for the ministry's candidate examination"; photos of ADB and his wife, Rosina; NY Times obituary of ADB; leaflets and newsletters from the Alpha and Omega Assembly, 1916-1950, n.d. (Box 385, Folder 2)
  - Beardslee, Alvord
    Beardslee received a B.D. from Yale Divinity School in 1953 and an S.T.M. in 1955. He served as a Professor of Religion at Hollins College, VA and as Congregational minister in the United Church of Christ, Salisbury. He was a Research Fellow at YDS in 1981-1982 and 1989-1990. He served on the Alumnal Board of YDS and was a Trustee of the Foundation for the Preservation of Sterling Divinity Quadrangle. These personal papers of Beardslee complement documentation regarding YDS and the Save the Quad movement in Record Group No. 53, YDS Memorabilia.
    - Foundation for the Preservation of Sterling Divinity Quadrangle documentation: meeting notes, administrative statements, campaign updates, Save the Quad publications, 1990s (Box 412, Folder 1-9)
    - Foundation for the Preservation of Sterling Divinity Quadrangle documentation: applications/scholarship, letters, 1990s (Box 413, Folder 1-2)
    - Yale Divinity School documentation, including "Dear Theo"(1996-1999), "Light and Verity", correspondence between Beardslee and Dean Richard Wood, 1990s (Box 413, Folder 3-15)
    - News clippings and publications regarding Yale Divinity School, 1990-2001 (Box 414, Folder 1-8)
    - Yale Divinity School documentation, including meetings/programs, religious services, notes, Association of Yale Alumni (AYA) letters and notes, 1990s (Box 415, Folder 1-9)
    - Yale Divinity School Alumnal Board meeting documents and notes, 1999-2002 (Box 416, Folder 1-9)
    - Yale Divinity School and Alumnal Board documenation, 1999-2000, n.d. (Box 417, Folder 1-8)
    - Yale and YDS documentation, incl. re. Yale Medal, Tercentennial, Pew Program, 2000, n.d. (Box 418, Folder 1-10)
  - Beebe, David Lewis
    1763 - Born in Trumbull, CT; 1785 - Graduated from Yale College; 1791 - Ordained and served as pastor of the Congregational Church in Woodbridge, CT; 1800 - Left position in Woodbridge because of ill health; 1803 - Died in Catskill, NY, where he had entered into business.
    - 259 manuscript sermons delivered in various Connecticut churches, most often in Woodbridge, CT. The sermons date from 1787 to 1798 and are arranged chronologically. One folder of undated, fragmentary, and attributed sermons follows the chronologically arranged sermons (Box 209–211)
  - Beebe, James
    1717/18 - Born in Danbury, CT; 1745 - Graduated from Yale College; 1746 - Ordained as pastor of church in Unity Parish (now Trumbull) CT; 1757, 1758 - Served as army chaplain during French and Indian Wars; 1776 - Served as army chaplain during Revolutionary War; 1785 - Died in Trumbull.
    - 60 manuscript sermons dating from 1753 to 1778. One folder of undated, fragmentary, and attributed sermons follows the chronologically arranged sermons (Box 212)
  - Bellamy, Joseph
    1719 Feb 20 - Born in Cheshire, CT; 1735 - Graduated from Yale College; 1735-1737 - Studied theology, partly with Jonathan Edwards; 1737 - Licensed to preach; 1738-1790 - Minister of a parish in Bethlehem, CT. Also preached through Connecticut for part of the year; 1750 - Published True Religion Delineated; 1758 - Published The Wisdom of God in the Permission of Sin; 1790 - Died.
    - Book of notes (23 pp.) possibly compiled by Bellamy while he was studying under Jonathan Edwards (ca. 1735-1737) (Box 179)
    - Bound volume (n.d.), holograph transcription of Bellamy's Upon the Nature of Love to God, Faith in Christ and Assurance of a Title to Eternal Life; contained in same volume: five transcribed letters to "Aspasio" from "Theron" (Box 179)
    - A. L. S. from Levi Hart to Joseph Bellamy; Preston, CT, August 10, n.d. - 1 p. (Box 179)
    - A. L. S. from Joseph Bellamy to his son Jonoath; Bethlem, CT, 1774 Feb 2 - 2 pp (Box 179)
    - A. L. S. from Joseph Bellamy to Rev. Mr. West, with 2pp. notes on infant circumcision; Bethlem, CT, 1781 Nov 15 (Box 179)
    - A. Ms. - Invitation to Bellamy from Synod of New York and Philadelphia (Elihu Spencer, Moderator) to annual meeting 1766 May; statement regarding proposed union of Synod of New York and Philadelpha and General Assocation of Connecticut (Box 179)
    - Typescript list of Bellamy holdings in the Yale Divinity Library and Yale University Library, 1960 Dec 2 (Box 179)
  - Bentley, Edward Warner
    1826 - Born in Tyringham, MA; 1850 - Graduated from Yale College; 1854 - B. D. from Hartford Theological Seminary; 1854-1881 - Pastor in Ellenville, NY; 1887 - Died in Canton Center, CT.
    - Bound volume of holograph notes taken by Bentley on sermons delivered primarily in the chapels of Yale College and Hartford Theological Seminary during the years 1845 to 1853. Sermons were delivered by Noah Porter, Lyman Beecher, Walter Clark, President Hitchcock, and others. (Box 213)
  - Bergmann, H. F. W.
    1899 Nov 11 - Born; Education included 6 years at seminary in Neuendettelsau; one year at University at Hamburg studying linguistics and languages of New Guinea and tropical medicine; 1926 - Arrived in New Guinea to begin mission work.